<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.21</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>John Joubert (serial killer)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2894578</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942944063</id>
      <parentid>942943858</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T21:06:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2001:569:78BA:4A00:4524:D959:3F35:B658</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16296" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2019}}
{{short description|American serial killer}}
{{Infobox serial killer
| name = John Joubert
| image = John Joseph Joubert IV.png
| image_size = 168px
| caption = Joubert's June 21, 1996 mugshot
| birth_name = John Joseph Joubert IV
| alias = The Nebraska Boy Snatcher&lt;br&gt;The Woodford Slasher
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1963|07|2}} 
| birth_place = [[Lawrence, Massachusetts|Lawrence]], [[Massachusetts]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1996|07|17|1963|07|2}}
| death_place = [[Lincoln, Nebraska|Lincoln]], [[Nebraska]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| cause = [[Electric chair]]
| victims = 3
| country = United States
| states = [[Maine]], [[Nebraska]]
| beginyear = August 22, 1982
| endyear = December 2, 1983
| apprehended = January 12, 1984
| sentence = [[Capital punishment|Death]] (October 9, 1984)&lt;br /&gt;[[Life imprisonment]] (October 15, 1990)
}}
'''John Joseph Joubert IV''' (July 2, 1963 – July 17, 1996) was an [[Americans|American]] [[serial killer]] convicted of the murders of three boys in [[Maine]] and [[Nebraska]]. He was [[capital punishment|executed]] in Nebraska by electric chair.

==Early life==
Joubert was born in [[Lawrence, Massachusetts]] on July 2, 1963. A bright child, he began reading at age 3 and borrowing books from a public library at 5. He was later found to have an [[Intelligence quotient|IQ]] of 123, signifying above average intelligence. Joubert's parents divorced when he was 8 years old, and he stayed to live with his mother, whom he greatly resented throughout his life as being excessively controlling. His mother forbade him to see his father, and often stood in the way of his developing connections with his peers who taunted him on the basis of his relatively small build from the time he was in grade school up until high school.

From a very young age, Joubert began having increasingly violent sadistic fantasies. According to three psychiatric reports prepared on Joubert in 1984, his earliest sadistic fantasies began at around the age of 6. These fantasies revolved around murdering and [[cannibalism|cannibalizing]] a neighborhood girl who babysat him. To one psychiatrist, he described having nothing personal against the girl, seeing her as "just someone to kill."&lt;ref name="mst960623"&gt;{{cite web | last = Clendenning | first = Alan | title =Trail of violence nears its end | work = Murderpedia (reprinting Telegram) | publisher = Maine Sunday Telegram  | date = June 23, 1996 | url = http://www.murderpedia.org/male.J/j1/joubert-john.htm | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1971, Joubert's mother moved them out of their former house into a rundown apartment. At this time, he was considered an outcast at school, and sought to compensate for these feelings of isolation by joining the Cub Scouts. It was around this time that his sadistic and homicidal fantasies progressed to the point where he contemplated murdering strangers on the streets, tying and gagging those who resisted him. In one later psychiatric report, he was described as saying that he derived pleasure from the thought of his victims saying "if you are going to do it, get it over with."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Pettit | first = Mark | title=A Need to Kill | year= 1990 | publisher= Ballantine Books |isbn=978-0-8041-0785-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1974, Joubert's mother moved his family to [[Portland, Maine]], and got a job as a bookkeeper. Here, his family settled in a two-story home in the middle-class Oakdale neighborhood. While he attended school in Portland, his problems with his peers began to intensify. He confessed at the age of 12 to having [[homosexual]] tendencies, and was further teased and ostracized because of it.

When he was 13, he stabbed a young girl with a pencil and felt [[sexual arousal|sexually stimulated]] when she cried in pain. The next day, he took a razor blade and slashed another girl as he biked past her. In another incident, he beat and nearly strangled another boy. He relished the power of [[bullying]], and continued to brutally attack his peers and younger children. At around age 16, he throttled an 8-year-old boy named Chris Day, almost killing him. Each offense occurred with gradually higher intensity, and each time Joubert successfully evaded getting caught.

In 1981, he graduated from [[Cheverus High School]] in Portland.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=5dA8AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Jy4MAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3678,1755520&amp;dq=john+joubert+cheverus&amp;hl=en Maine authorities want to interview Joubert in Nebraska] ''Bangor Daily News'', October 19, 1984&lt;/ref&gt;

==Murders==
On August 22, 1982, 11-year-old Richard "Ricky" Stetson had gone jogging on the 3.5 mile long [[Back Cove, (Portland, Maine)|Back Cove]] Trail in Portland, Maine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Ramsland |first1=Katherine |last2=McGrain |first2=Patrick N. |date=December 21, 2009 |title=Inside the Minds of Sexual Predators |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gngG9zPmNKMC&amp;pg=PA64|publisher=Praeger, Frederick A. |page=64 |isbn=978-0313379604 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://trails.org/our-trails/back-cove-trail/ |title=Back Cove Trail |website=trails.org |publisher= |accessdate=November 10, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; When he had not returned by dark, his parents called the police. The next day, a motorist saw the boy's body on the side of [[Interstate 295 (Maine)|US&amp;nbsp;I-295]]. The attacker appeared to have attempted to undress him, and then stabbed and strangled him. A suspect was arrested for the murder, but his teeth did not match a bite mark on Stetson's body, so he was released after a year and a half in custody. No additional leads presented themselves in the case until January 1984.

Danny Joe Eberle, 13 years old, disappeared while delivering the ''[[Omaha World-Herald]]'' newspaper on Sunday, September 18, 1983, in [[Bellevue, Nebraska]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/a-13-year-olds-dead-body-turns-up|title=A 13-year-old's dead body turns up - Sep 21, 1983 - HISTORY.com|work=HISTORY.com|access-date=February 7, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; His brother, who also delivered papers, had not seen him, but he did remember being followed by a white man in a tan car on previous days. It was found that Eberle had delivered only three of the 70 newspapers on his route. At the address of his fourth delivery, his bicycle was discovered along with the rest of the newspapers. There appeared to be no sign of a struggle. Joubert would later describe how he had approached Eberle, drawn a knife, and covered the boy's mouth with his hand. He instructed Eberle to follow him to his truck and drove him to a gravel road outside the town.

After a three-day search, Eberle's body was discovered in a patch of high grass alongside a gravel road some 4 miles (6&amp;nbsp;km) from his bicycle. He had been stripped to his underwear, his feet and hands had been bound, and his mouth had been taped with [[surgical tape]]. Knife wounds across his body suggested he had been tortured before death. In addition, Joubert had stabbed him nine times. As a kidnapping, the crime came under the jurisdiction of the federal government of the United States, so the FBI was called in.&lt;ref&gt;''The Casebook of Forensic Detection'' {{ISBN|0-471-07650-3}} p. 285&lt;/ref&gt;

The investigation followed several leads, including a young man who was arrested for [[child sexual abuse|molesting]] two young boys about a week after the crime. He failed a polygraph test and had a false alibi but did not fit the profile the FBI had created for the murderer. He was released because of the lack of evidence. Other known pedophiles in the area were also questioned, but the case went cold due to a scarcity of evidence.

On December 2, 1983, Christopher Walden, age 12, disappeared in [[Papillion, Nebraska]], about 3 miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) from where Eberle's body had been found.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.upi.com/Archives/1983/12/06/Kidnapped-childs-body-found/7156439534800/|title=Kidnapped child's body found|work=UPI|access-date=February 7, 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Witnesses again said they saw a white man in a tan car. Joubert said that he had driven up to Walden as he walked, showed him the sheath of his knife and ordered him into the car. 

After driving to some railway lines out of town he ordered Walden to strip to his underwear. Walden did so, but then refused to lie down. After a brief struggle Joubert overpowered Walden, and stabbed him. It was later found Walden's throat had been cut so deeply he was nearly decapitated. Walden's body was found two days later, 5 miles (8&amp;nbsp;km) from town. Although the crimes were similar, there were differences: Walden had not been bound, had been concealed better, and was thought to have been killed immediately after being abducted.

==Arrest==
On January 11, 1984, a preschool teacher in the area of the murders called the police to say that she had seen a young man driving in the area. There are conflicting stories as to what occurred, whether the car was loitering or just driving around. When the driver saw the teacher writing down his license plate, he stopped and threatened her before fleeing. The car was not tan, but was traced and found to be rented by John Joubert, an enlisted radar technician from Offutt Air Force Base. It turned out that his own car, a tan [[Chevrolet Nova|Nova sedan]], was being repaired.

A search warrant was issued, and rope consistent with that used to bind Danny Joe Eberle was found in his barracks room. The FBI found that the unusual rope had been made for the United States military in [[South Korea]]. Under interrogation, Joubert claimed he got it from the scoutmaster in the troop in which he was an assistant.

[[Robert K. Ressler]], the FBI's head profiler at the time, had immediate access to the information about the two boys in Nebraska and worked up a hypothetical description which matched Joubert in every regard. While he was presenting the case of the two Nebraska boys to a training class at the FBI academy at [[Quantico, Virginia|Quantico]], a police officer from [[Portland, Maine]] noted the similarities to a case in his jurisdiction which took place where Joubert lived prior to joining the Air Force. Bite-mark comparisons proved that Joubert was responsible for the Maine killing in addition to those in Nebraska. Ressler and the Maine investigators came to believe that Joubert joined the military to get away from Maine after the murder of the Stetson boy.&lt;REF NAME=RESSLER&gt;Ressler, Robert K. and Tom Shachtman, ''Whoever Fights Monsters: My Twenty Years Hunting Serial Killers for the FBI.'' New York: St. Martin's Press, 1992.  ''See'' Chapter 5, "Death of a Newsboy," pp. 93–112.  {{ISBN|0-312-07883-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further investigation in Maine revealed two crimes between the pencil-stabbing of the 9-year-old girl in 1979 and the murder of Stetson in 1982. In 1980, Ressler's investigation revealed that Joubert had slashed a 9-year-old boy and a female teacher in her mid-20s who both "had been cut rather badly, and were lucky to be alive."&lt;REF NAME=RESSLER/&gt;

==Trials and appeals==
Joubert then confessed to killing the two boys, and on January 12, 1984, he was charged with their murders. After initially pleading not guilty, he changed his plea to guilty. There were several [[psychiatry|psychiatric]] evaluations performed on Joubert. One characterised him as having [[obsessive-compulsive disorder]] and [[Sexual sadism disorder|sadistic tendencies]], and suffering from [[schizoid personality disorder]].&lt;ref name="trutv"&gt;{{cite web| last = Ramsland| first = Katherine| title =John Joubert, Nebraska Boy Snatcher| work = Crime Library| publisher = TruTv| date =| url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/predators/john_joubert/index.html| accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|13}} 

He was found to have been not [[psychosis|psychotic]] at the time of the crimes. A panel of three judges [[death sentence|sentenced him to death]] for both counts. Joubert was also sentenced to [[life imprisonment]] in [[Maine]] (which did not have the death penalty) in 1990 for the murder of Ricky Stetson after Joubert's teeth were found to match the bite mark.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/news/crime/serial-killer-john-joubert-days-slaying-kids-article-1.3501029|title=How serial killer John Joubert's days of slaying kids came to end|work=NY Daily News|access-date=February 7, 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1995, Joubert filed a writ of [[habeas corpus]] to the [[United States federal courts]] over the death sentences. His lawyers argued that the aggravating factor of "exceptional depravity" was [[U.S. Constitution|unconstitutionally]] vague, and the court agreed. The state of Nebraska [[appeal]]ed to the [[United States District Court for the District of Nebraska]], which overturned the appeal, saying that he had shown sadistic behavior by [[torture|torturing]] Eberle and Walden.

Joubert was executed on July 17, 1996 by the state of Nebraska in the electric chair. He was the second person executed in Nebraska since the death penalty was reintroduced in the state in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.upi.com/Archives/1996/07/17/Child-killer-executed-in-Nebraska/9576837576000/|title=Child killer executed in Nebraska|work=UPI|access-date=February 7, 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An appeal to the [[Nebraska Supreme Court]] over whether the electric chair in Nebraska is a [[Eighth Amendment to the United States Constitution|cruel and unusual punishment]] revealed that during his execution, Joubert suffered a four-inch brain blister on the top of his head and blistering on both sides of his head above his ears.&lt;ref&gt;[http://journalstar.com/news/state-and-regional/judge-details-why-he-thinks-electric-chair-is-a-cruel/article_adb36116-7270-5eba-be30-0a6dc654f14b.html Judge details why he thinks electric chair is a cruel penalty]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of serial killers in the United States]]

==References==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist}}

;General references
*{{cite web | last = Ramsland | first = Katherine | title = John Joubert, Nebraska Boy Snatcher | work = truTV Crime Library | url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/predators/john_joubert/12.html | accessdate = }}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20050424034221/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?did=1421&amp;scid=64 Nebraska Supreme Court to Hear Electric Chair Challenge] from [[Death Penalty Information Center]]
*[http://dcs-inmatesearch.ne.gov/Corrections/InmateDisplayServlet?DcsId=35946 Inmate Details: 35946 – John Joubert]. ''Nebraska Department of Correctional Services''. Retrieved on 2007-08-17.

==External links==
* State v. Joubert: [https://law.justia.com/cases/nebraska/supreme-court/1986/843-8.html Details of Joubert's 1986 appeal against his convictions]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Joubert, John}}
[[Category:1963 births]]
[[Category:1996 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century executions by Nebraska]]
[[Category:20th-century executions of American people]]
[[Category:20th-century American criminals]]
[[Category:American male criminals]]
[[Category:American serial killers]]
[[Category:American murderers of children]]
[[Category:American prisoners sentenced to life imprisonment]]
[[Category:American people convicted of murder]]
[[Category:Crimes in Omaha, Nebraska]]
[[Category:Executed American serial killers]]
[[Category:Executed people from Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Male serial killers]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Maine]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Nebraska]]
[[Category:People executed by Nebraska by electric chair]]
[[Category:People from Lawrence, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:People from Portland, Maine]]
[[Category:People with schizoid personality disorder]]
[[Category:People with obsessive–compulsive disorder]]
[[Category:Prisoners sentenced to life imprisonment by Maine]]
[[Category:Violence against women]]
[[Category:Violence against men in North America]]
[[Category:Cheverus High School alumni]]
[[Category:People executed for murder]]
[[Category:Crime in Maine]]
[[Category:Crime in Nebraska]]
[[Category:Criminals from Maine]]
[[Category:Criminals from Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Criminals from Nebraska]]
[[Category:1982 murders in the United States]]
[[Category:1983 murders in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>5dvij0pq12ljnolmn10olk9i11nn2vz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
